Finding Aid for Michael T. Alexander papers, 1968-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michael T. Alexander papers 1968-1994 1982-1992
Alexander, Michael T.
2012025 Aa 2
Michael T. Alexander was a member of the research staff of the University of Michigan's Computing Center and Information Technology Division Research Systems from 1965 to 1996. Collection contains records of Alexander's duties as well as extensive documentation for the Michigan Terminal System, including manuals and systems reports.
8 linear feet in 10 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records received through Michael Alexander (donor no. 10570 ).
Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Michael T. Alexander joined the University of Michigan's Computing Center in 1965 as a Research Assistant.
In the mid-1960s, the staff of the UM Computing Center relied on IBM 7090 hardware and an operating system, the UM Executive System (UMES), of their own design. The limited memory available to the IBM 7090 and the high cost of its operation demanded the use of "batch processing," in which programs were run immediately after one another with minimal human intervention. Batch processing ensured that the university's expensive computing resources were used cost-effectively, but did so at the price of requiring users to wait hours or days for project results. However, in 1966 new developments in virtual memory architecture inspired the staff of the Computing Center to draft a proposal for a terminal-oriented, time-sharing operating system that would allow users to interact with their programs and receive immediate results.[1]
The Computing Center staff took their time-sharing proposal to IBM which led, after a period of close collaboration, to the development of a one-of-a-kind IBM System 360/66M computer ('M' for 'Michigan'). When project delays prevented IBM from delivering software to support the new hardware's time-sharing capability, Michael T. Alexander and Donald W. Boettner led the development of an in-house time-sharing operating system, the Michigan Terminal System (MTS). The low level supervisor or kernel of the system was the UM Multiprogramming Supervisor (UMMPS) which controlled the execution of multiple instances of "job programs," one of which was MTS which made time-sharing possible.[2]
MTS was released to the UM campus in May, 1967. By 1970 the system could support 58 simultaneous users on nearly 200 terminals providing access to MTS on the UM campus and from other universities. While MTS had little difficulty responding to requests for 100,000 jobs per month or more, such demands were growing beyond the capacity of the IBM 360/67 computers on which it ran. The University of British Columbia Computing Centre had adapted MTS to run on IBM 370 and Extended Architecture (XA) systems, but the UM Computing Center preferred the superior speed and reliability of the Amdahl 470V/6 computer. UM was the first university to use the Amdahl computer. While other universities soon migrated to Amdahl, the system would remain a part of the UM computing infrastructure through the mid-1980s.[3]
In addition to the University of Michigan and the University of British Columbia, there were five other member institutions of the MTS Consortium: the University of Alberta, Wayne State University, the Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Simon Fraser University, and NUMAC ("Northumbrian Universities Multiple Access Computer," a collaboration between the University of Newcastle upon Tyne, the Durham University, and Newcastle Polytechnic). Each of the member institutions played a significant part in the development of MTS, particularly in the design, implementation, and testing of features and services. Other notable users of MTS included Michigan State University, Hewlett-Packard, and NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center.[4]
In the early 1970s a parallel initiative, the Michigan Educational Research Information Triad (MERIT) linked the computer systems of the University of Michigan, Michigan State University, and Wayne State University. The MERIT network was independent of MTS, but in practice the two projects were closely associated, and the University of Michigan provided all hosting and staff support for the new network. By the late 1970s, Merit had begun to expand to other Michigan universities as part of its mission to provide advanced and expensive computer resources to smaller institutions that could not otherwise afford them. Services provided by the Merit network would include access to the Telnet network by 1976 as well as access to the Internet in 1985. Communication processing technology developed for Merit would lead to the creation of UMnet in 1983.[5]
MTS also provided innovative services. In 1975 graduate student Robert Parnes created CONFER, an early conferencing system for private electronic mail exchange, open or invitation-only group discussion on MTS and on other systems linked to MTS via the Merit network. Email service to remote users on other systems was added in September 1983 when MTS joined the MAILNET project, a joint effort by sixteen universities and EDUCOM (the precursor to EDUCAUSE). The increasing popularity of microcomputers in the early 1980s also led the Computing Center staff to develop programs, which would allow the use of Apple II and IBM PC computers as terminals on the MTS system.[6]
The development of popular features, such as remote access from other networks, added to the growing demand placed on MTS by students and faculty. In 1985, a second system was secured for the increased use. This second system was named "UB" or "U-Blue" to distinguish it from the first system, which was retroactively, designated "UM" or "U-Maize." A third MTS system was created for the UM Department of Human Genetics. [7]
In 1985 the Computing Center was merged into the Information Technology Division, a new unit intended to shift the university's computing resources away from centralized mainframes in favor of distributed networks and support for microcomputers, such as the Apple II. The increasing popularity of microcomputers coupled with other trends in computer technology during that time eventually led to the replacement of MTS largely by Unix-based networked servers with TCP/IP support for internet connectivity. End-user support for MTS ended on June 30, 1996, and the UM systems themselves were shut down on May 30, 1997.
The last member of the MTS Consortium to have an MTS system in operation was Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute. That system was shut down in June 1999. However, MTS can still be run on IBM System 370 emulators. [8]
----------------------------
1. "A Faster Cratchit," Blanchard Hiatt. Research News, Vol XXVII. No. 1, January 1976, pp 9-10; "MTS: An Overview," Susan Topol. May 1996 Information Technology Digest, published by the University of Michigan Information Technology Division. Retrieved on October 11, 2001, from http://www.clock.org/~jss/work/mts/overview.html; Email message from Bob Alexander, April 16, 2012 to Nancy Deromedi.
2. "A Faster Cratchit," p. 16, 18-21; "Michigan Terminal System," Donald W. Boettner and Michael T. Alexander. ACM SIGOPS Operating Systems Review, Vol. 4 Issue 4, December 1970, p. 7; Jeff Ogden, "The Michigan Terminal System." Retrieved on January 11, 2012 from http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michigan_Terminal_System
3. "MTS: An Overview," Susan Topol. May 1996 Information Technology Digest, published by the University of Michigan Information Technology Division. Retrieved on October 11, 2001, from http://www.clock.org/~jss/work/mts/overview.html
4. "Merit-Who, What, and Why," Eric M. Aupperle. Retrieved on January 24, 2012, from http://www.merit.edu/about/history/pdf/NSFNET_final.pdf; "Faster Cratchit," p. 22; "Merit Network," Mark Riordan. Retrieved on January 24, 2012, from https://www.msu.edu/~mrr/mycomp/mts/merit.htm; History timeline of the Merit Network. Retrieved on January 25, 2012, from: http://www.merit.edu/about/history/timeline_1980.php
5. "CONFER (software)," Jeff Ogden. Retrieved on January 25, 2012, from: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CONFER_%28software%29; "MTS System Architecture," Jeff Ogden. Retrieved on January 25, 2012, from: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MTS_system_architecture#Electronic_mail; "Computing at Michigan," Thomas Madden. Retrieved on January 4, 2012, from: http://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/handle/2027.42/79605
6. "Michigan Terminal System," Jeff Ogden. Retrieved from http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michigan_Terminal_System on February 3, 2012.
The Michael T. Alexander papers document the work of Alexander and other University of Michigan Computing Center programmers and staff in developing the Michigan Terminal System (MTS) and other software.
The title of this collection acknowledges Michael T. Alexander as the primary collector and donor of the papers. The collection includes a varsity of administrative records relating to MTS with an emphasis on the development of certain aspects of the Michigan Terminal System environment such as email.
Researchers should be aware that these records use the term "MTS" in three different respects:
MTS the UMMPS Job Program with which most end-users interact
MTS the software system, including UMMPS, the MTS and other Job Programs, Command Language Subsystems (CLSs), public files (programs), and documentation; and
MTS the time-sharing service offered at a particular site, including the MTS software system, the hardware used to run MTS, the staff that supported MTS and assisted end-users, and the associated administrative policies and procedures.
In the first instance, "MTS" would be considered a part of the UM Multiprogramming Supervisor (UMMPS). In the other instances, however, the UMMPS would be considered a part of "MTS." The researcher should, therefore, exercise caution when assuming a particular hierarchical relationship between MTS and UMMPS in these records.
The records of the Michael T. Alexander collection are organized in six series: Administrative Records; Budget Material; Distribution Tapes and Documentation; Software Manuals and Programming; Systems Reports; and Vendors.
Subjects:
Alexander, Michael T.; Computer networks.; Information technology.; MTS (Computer system); Michigan Terminal System.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Information Technology Division.; University of Michigan. Computing Center.
- Administrative Records 1971-1992
  The Administrative Records series contains minutes, reports, and correspondence pertinent to the development and maintenance of MTS and other Computing Center and Information Technology Division initiatives from 1974 to 1992. Notable records in this series include:
  The minutes of monthly meetings of "Committee A," which addressed a wide range of issues of concern to the Computing Center staff.
  An extensive set of printouts from online forum sessions which provide transcripts of detailed, and often technical, discussions concerning various issues in MTS development.
  "The Future of MTS" includes committee minutes, survey results, and reports that were used to anticipate trends in technology and in the organizational requirements of ITD in the early 1990s.
  The Information Technology Architecture Committee addressed several critical issues including user access and authorization; core network architecture; email; file systems; connectivity among operating systems; and support for applications and peripherals.
  Records pertaining to organizational planning meetings from 1989 provide insight into the organizational transition from the Computing Center to the new ITD. And the L3 Project documents a proposal in 1985 to buy a supercomputer, the ELXSI 6400 Multiprocessor System.
  - Apple Computer systems and development circa 1992 (Box 1)
  - Capacity Task Force 1990 (Box 1)
  - Computer Use Pricing, circa 1984 (Box 1)
  - Computing Center Committee A, Minutes 1974-1986, 1990, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Computing Center Committee A, Miscellaneous 1971-1987, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Computing Center Organization Chart 1986 (Box 1)
  - Computing Center User Services Planning Team Report 1986 (Box 1)
  - Computing Center User Survey 1984 (Box 1)
  - Computing Policy Committee 1987 (Box 1)
  - Development and Deployment Weekly Staff Meeting 1991 (Box 1)
  - Distributed Computing, draft notes 1991 (Box 1)
  - EDUCOM 1989 Annual Meeting, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Electronic Mail and Freedom of Information Act 1990 (Box 1)
  - Electronic Mail Filtering 1991 (Box 1)
  - Electronic Mail Migration to Internet 1986 (Box 1)
  - Electronic Mail Services and Concerns circa 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - Electronic Mail Working Committee 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - Ethics in Information Technology Workshop 1991 (Box 1)
  - Forum Discussions by MTS Staff (Box 1)
  - 1978-1984, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Forum Discussions by MTS Staff (Box 2)
    - 1978-1984, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Future of MTS 1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Future of MTS 1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Housing and Residence Hall Computing Network, final version and notes 1990 (Box 2)
  - Information Technology Architecture Committee 1986-1987, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Information Technology Architecture Committee 1987-1988, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Information Technology Division Organizational Planning 1989, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Information Technology Division User Services Needs Assessment Survey 1987 (Box 2)
  - Information Technology Working Group Reports 1992 (Box 2)
  - Institutional File System Project 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - International Use of MTS, Correspondence 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - ISDN Deployment Planning Meeting 1992 (Box 2)
  - L3 Project 1985, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - MicroGroup 1986 (Box 3)
  - MTS Naming Scheme, no date (Box 3)
  - MTS Workshop 1990 (Box 3)
  - Network Service Proposals 1986 (Box 3)
  - Network Traffic Model Data 1987 (Box 3)
  - Planning Advisory Group, support documents 1990 (Box 3)
  - Primary Research Appointment and Promotion Guidelines 1988 (Box 3)
  - Research Systems Computing Services 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Research Systems Monthly Management Meeting I 1991 (Box 3)
  - Research Systems Monthly Management Meeting II 1991 (Box 3)
  - Research Systems Monthly Management Meeting 1992 (Box 3)
  - Uniqnames 1990 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Statistical Program Census 1976 (Box 3)
- Budget Material 1979-1995
  The Budget Material series includes minutes from planning and priority meetings; project reviews; and workforce reduction proposals from 1979 to 1995. The bulk of these records pertain to the years 1985-1987 and 1990-1993.
  - 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - 1985-1986 (Box 3)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - 1991-1992, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Research Systems Budget Reduction Exercise 1990 (Box 3)
  - 1991-1992 Budget Planning and Priorities Group Meeting, 1991 (Box 3)
  - 1991-1992 Budget Planning and Priorities Group Projects Review, 1991 (Box 3)
  - 1991-1992 Budget Reduction Summaries by Unit, 1991 (Box 3)
  - 1991-1992 Information Technology Policy Committee, 1991 (Box 3)
  - 1991-1992 Senior Management Retreat (Box 3)
  - Budget Material, Research Studies Reduction in Force 1992 (Box 3)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - 1993-1994 Budget Planning Steering Committee, 1990-1992 (Box 3)
  - 1993-1994 Project Clump Summary (Box 4)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - 1994-1995 Budget Working Group (Box 4)
- Distribution Tapes and Documentation 1968-1996
  The Distribution Tapes and Documentation series provides printouts of the program files that constitute MTS and its various systems. These include driver files, indexes, line listings, logs, and notes. Electronic versions of these materials are also part of the Computing Center (University of Michigan) record group at the Bentley Historical Library. These files are accessible via an archival collection in the University of Michigan's institutional repository, Deep Blue, at
  http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/89588
  .
  - Distribution 1.0 Log File and 10 Line Listing 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 1.0 Modification 1, Log File and 10 Line Listing 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 2.0 Log File and 10 Line Listing 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 2.1 Notes and Log File 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 2.2 Log File, 10 Line Listing, and Driver File Listing 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 2.3 Log File 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 3.0 Log File 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 3.0 Notes and Driver File 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 3.1 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 3.2 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 4.0 Log File 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 4.0 Notes and Driver File 1996, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Distribution 4.1 Driver File, Index, Notes, and Log, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Distribution 4.2 Driver File, Index, Notes, and Log, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Distribution 4.2 Log (copy failed) 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 4.2A (Redistribution 16) Driver File and Log File 1996, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Distribution 4.2B Log File, Driver File, and MTS Forum 1996 (Box 4)
  - Distribution 4.3 Driver File, Index, Notes, and Log
    - 1996, 1 folders (Box 4)
  - Distribution 4.3 Driver File, Index, Notes, and Log (Box 5)
    - 1996, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Distribution 5.0 Change Forms 1996 (Box 5)
  - Distribution 5.0 Driver File, Index, Notes, and Log 1996, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Distribution 5.1 Index 1996 (Box 5)
  - Distribution 5.1 Driver File, Notes, and Log 1996, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Distribution 5.1 Log (Partial?) 1996 (Box 5)
  - Distribution 6.0 Notes, Newsys, Oldsys, MTS Doc, and Index 1996 (Box 5)
  - Distribution 6.0 Driver File List 1996, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Distribution 6.0 Log
    - 1996, 1 folders (Box 5)
  - Distribution 6.0 Log (Box 6)
    - 1996, 1 folders (Box 6)
- Software Manuals and Programming 1970-1989
  The Software Manuals and Programming series consists of four MTS manuals (out of a total of twenty-four), and a number of other manuals for various programs and sub-systems that were part of or were supported by MTS. Records include "Firefighter's Guides," which provided introductions to various components of MTS for new systems administrators. Several records pertain to "intertask communication" which is a mechanism that allows various parts of the system to communicate with each other. This series includes some over-sized material.
  - Accessing UMNet from the Internet 1987 (Box 6)
  - Accounting Streams and Records 1985 (Box 6)
  - Arc Programs 1987 (Box 6)
  - AUTOSTART, Automatic Scheduling of MTS Jobs 1981 (Box 8)
  - AUTOSTART Considerations 1981 (Box 8)
  - CDUPDATE, A Context --Directed Update Program 1981 (Box 8)
  - Code Generator Specification Language 1982 (Box 6)
  - Command Extensions and Macros (Box 6)
  - CONFIG 1983, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - CPU Scheduling 1988 (Box 6)
  - Device Control Command Standard Proposal 1980 (Box 8)
  - Device Support Routine (DSR) Specifications 1980 (Box 8)
  - Disk Cache Use Predicted Effects,1981 (Box 8)
  - Electronic Mail Programs 1985 (Box 6)
  - EVATTN Subroutine, no date (Box 6)
  - Firefighter's Guides circa 1987 (Box 6)
  - Fortran/VS Under MTS, no date (Box 6)
  - FORUM Computer Conferencing Program 1981 (Box 6)
  - Fsmessage Command 1984 (Box 6)
  - Gated CC Routines, no date (Box 6)
  - Hierarchical File System Utilizing Command Macros 1987 (Box 6)
  - IBX Connections to Host Computers 1986 (Box 6)
  - Intertask Communication Facility 1977 (Box 6)
  - Intertask Communication in MTS 1978 (Box 9)
  - Intertask Exerciser 1975 (Box 9)
  - Intertask Exerciser Monitor 1978 (Box 9)
  - Intertask Exerciser Repertoire Routine I 1980 (Box 9)
  - Intertask Exerciser Repertoire Routine II 1980 (Box 9)
  - Intertask Exit Buffer Printer 1978 (Box 9)
  - Intertask Job Program 1981 (Box 9)
  - Intertask List Buffer Printer 1978 (Box 9)
  - Intertask Message Routine 1978 (Box 9)
  - Intertask Sense Buffer Printer 1978 (Box 9)
  - ISDOS Project Utilities for MTS $ACCOUNTING Data 1980 (Box 6)
  - Job Dumps, A Fire-Fighter's Guide 1980 (Box 8)
  - $List Command Extension Proposal 1980 (Box 8)
  - Make Command 1988 (Box 6)
  - Memory Management, no date (Box 6)
  - Message Archiving Subroutine Package for $Message and $Fsmessage 1987 (Box 6)
  - Message Routine 1979 (Box 6)
  - MTS Maintenance Procedures circa 1983 (Box 6)
  - MTS Manual, Volume 3, System Subroutine Descriptions 1981, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - MTS Manual, Volume 5, System Services 1983 (Box 6)
  - MTS Manual, Volume 15, Format and Text 360 (Box 6)
  - MTS Manual, Volume 20, PASCAL in MTS (Box 6)
  - Named Address Spaces 1984, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Newcastle Intertask Communication Scheme I 1975 (Box 9)
  - Newcastle Intertask Communication Scheme II 1975 (Box 9)
  - NUMAC HELP System, no date (Box 6)
  - NUMAC Intertask Communication Scheme 1975 (Box 9)
  - OSIRIS II MTS Users Manual 1970 (Box 6)
  - PAGE WATCH, a PLUS PDP System Watcher 1981 (Box 8)
  - Paging Drum Measure Results 1980 (Box 8)
  - PMF Program Management Facility 1984 (Box 6)
  - Preliminary Design of a JOBS Replacement 1979 (Box 8)
  - Program Management Facility for MTS, Status Report 1980 (Box 8)
  - PROLOG/MTS Users Manual 1980 (Box 6)
  - Proposal for a New MTS Catalog 1980 (Box 8)
  - Proposed System Improvements 1981-1984 (Box 6)
  - Proprietary Software Running Under MTS 1982 (Box 6)
  - PsX Postscript File Converter 1987 (Box 6)
  - RAMROD Proposal for New Version 1977 (Box 6)
  - RAMROD System Maintenance Utility, no date (Box 6)
  - Resource Manager circa 1989 (Box 6)
  - Routines Added by NUMAC to UMMPS 1975 (Box 8)
  - Scan Program, no date (Box 6)
  - Scratch File Initialization 1980 (Box 8)
  - Software Management Under MTS 1986 (Box 6)
  - Subtasking in MTS 1986 (Box 6)
  - Subtasking Monitor and MTS Device Support Routines 1980 (Box 6)
  - Supervisor Call Proposal for Intertask Communication 1971 (Box 9)
  - Switched Multimegabit Data Service (SMDS) 1979 (Box 8)
  - System Control Blocks, a Preliminary Version 1979 (Box 8)
  - TABLES Control Section Generation Process 1985 (Box 6)
  - Tango String Processing Language 1983 (Box 6)
  - UBC and UM Time Package Comparisons 1978 (Box 8)
  - UBC Intertask at UM 1980 (Box 9)
  - UBCNET Server Device Support Routine Description 1982 (Box 6)
  - UBC Plus Programming Language 1986 (Box 6)
  - U-Blue System Move to IBM 3090circa 1987 (Box 6)
  - User Datagram Protocol (UDP) Interface to MTS via Merit, no date (Box 6)
  - Uniform User Interface 1981 (Box 6)
  - User-Directory Routines 1989 (Box 6)
  - VMN, Virtual Machine Program 1981 (Box 8)
  - VSE (Virtual Storage Extended) System 1987 (Box 6)
  - Wiersba Visual Editor, no date (Box 6)
  - WRITEI Changes 1988 (Box 6)
  - WRITEI Code (Assembler H Code) 1986, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Xerox 9700 Printer Support, 1979 (Box 8)
- Systems Reports 1968-1991
  The Systems Reports series includes several benchmark tests which compared the technical capabilities of IBM, Amdahl, and NAS computers. The series also contains several performance tests of MTS itself, including sample printouts of the "Counts and Times from Supervisor and PDP" report, which was run regularly from 1972 to 1991. This series includes some over-sized material.
  - Benchmark Test, Stack Depth Samples, and Timetally Experiments 1973-1978 (Box 7)
  - Benchmark Tests of Amdahl and IBM Mainframes 1975 (Box 7)
  - Benchmark Tests of Amdahl and NAS Mainframes 1983 (Box 7)
  - Benchmark Tests of Amdahl and IBM Mainframes 1986, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Benchmark Tests of MTS Services 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - Counts and Times from Supervisor and PDP 1972-1991 (Box 10)
  - Downtime Statistics 1969-1989, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Interrupts 1968 (Box 7)
  - Usage Statistics circa 1968-1972 (Box 7)
  - Usage Statistics, Amdahl Mainframe 1969-1983 (Box 7)